A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of the Secretary, Alsie Falconer, and General Files FA584
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of the Secretary, Alsie Falconer, and General Files
1967-1992, bulk 1980-1983
1980-1983
Rockefeller Archive Center
Falconer, Alsie
Ford Foundation
FA584
6.55 Cubic Feet 5 record storage boxes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series by file type.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Chronological Files, 1982-1983, 1991-1992
Series II. Subject Files, 1967-1983
Series III. Pending Grant Files, 1976-1983
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
Contains correspondence, subject files and grant files.
- Chronological Files, 1982-1983, 1991-1992; I
  - 1982 (Aug) Chronological Correspondence, 1982 August (Box 1)
  - 1982 (Sep) Chronological Correspondence, 1982 September (Box 1)
  - 1982 (Sep-Oct) Chronological Correspondence, 1982 September-October (Box 1)
  - 1982 (Oct) Chronological Correspondence, 1982 October (Box 1)
  - 1982 (Nov) Chronological Correspondence (1 of 2), 1982 November (Box 1)
  - 1982 (Nov) Chronological Correspondence (1 of 2), 1982 November (Box 1)
  - 1982 (Dec) Chronological Correspondence, 1982 December (Box 1)
  - 1983 (Jan) Chronological Correspondence, 1983 January (Box 1)
  - 1983 (Feb) Chronological Correspondence, 1983 February (Box 1)
  - 1983 (Mar) Chronological Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1983 (Apr) Chronological Correspondence, 1983 April (Box 1)
  - 1983 (May) Chronological Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1983 (Jun) Chronological Correspondence (1 of 2), 1983 June (Box 1)
  - 1983 (Jun) Chronological Correspondence (2 of 2), 1983 June (Box 1)
  - 1983 (Jul) Chronological Correspondence, 1983 July (Box 1)
  - 1991 Chronological Correspondence, 1991 April 26-July 25 (Box 2)
  - 1991 Chronological Correspondence, 1991 June 6-September 23 (Box 2)
  - 1991 Chronological Correspondence, 1991 September 6-November 14 (Box 2)
  - 1991/1992 Chronological Correspondence, 1991 December 26-1992 April 2 (Box 2)
  - 1992 Chronological Correspondence, 1992 March 11-May 14 (Box 2)
  - 1992 Chronological Correspondence, 1992 April 13-July 22 (Box 2)
  - 1992 Chronological Correspondence, 1992 September 3-November 13 (Box 3)
  - Bernstein, Alison Chronological Files, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Biddle, Sheila Chronological Files, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Cary, Linn Chronological Files, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Coolen, Marion Chronological Files, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Hardy, Gladys Chronological Files (1 of 5), 1982 January-February (Box 3)
  - Hardy, Gladys Chronological Files (2 of 5), 1982 March-April (Box 3)
  - Hardy, Gladys Chronological Files (3 of 5), 1982 May-June (Box 3)
  - Hardy, Gladys Chronological Files (4 of 5), 1982 July-August (Box 3)
  - Hardy, Gladys Chronological Files (5 of 5), 1982 September-December (Box 3)
  - Mayleas, Ruth Chronological Files, 1983 (Box 3)
  - McCarthy, Nancy Chronological Files, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Thompson, Marcia Chronological Files, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
- Subject Files, 1967-1983; II
  - Education and Culture Annual Report -- Drafts, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Committee Meeting (3/24/1982) -- "A Supplement to Part II - Results", 1982 March (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Committee Meeting (3/24/1982) -- Marcia Thompson, MATT Introductory Remarks, 1982 March 24 (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Committee Meeting (3/24/1982) -- Opening Remarks by Gladys Chang Hardy, 1982 March 24 (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Committee Meeting (3/24/1982) -- Presentation to EC Committee Re: Delhi Office Culture Program by Lincoln Chen, 1982 March 24 (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Committee Meeting (3/24/1982) -- Program Outline, 1982 June 4 (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Committee Meeting (3/24/1982) -- Stabilization Strategy (incl. proposal for creation of National Arts Stabilization Fund), 1982 March (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Docket "Grants and DAPs from Appropriations and Delegated Authority Grants" Prepared for Board of Trustees Meeting (3/24-25/1982) (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Paper -- Final Draft -- "Education and Culture - A Discussion Paper" by Gladys Hardy, 1982 March 17 (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Paper -- Old Drafts -- Creative and Performing Arts, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Paper -- Old Drafts -- Cultural Preservation, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Paper -- Old Drafts -- Development of Talent and Resources, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Paper -- Old Drafts -- Introduction and Assorted Chapters, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Paper -- Old Drafts -- Policy Analysis and Dissemination, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Education and Culture Paper -- Old Drafts -- Quality of Scholarships, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Educational Testing Service -- Conference on Latino College Students (Jan 28-29, 1983) (Box 3)
  - Financial Aid Sources -- Correspondence, Lists, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Ford Foundation Program Reorganization and Reassignment of Grants, 1967; 1981 (Box 3)
  - Minorities in Higher Education -- Commission on the Higher Education of Minorities, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - Minorities in Higher Education -- NFF/ETS -- Annual Directory of Fellows, 1975-1979 (Box 3)
  - Minorities in Higher Education -- NFF/ETS -- Application Forms, 1975-1979 (Box 3)
  - Minorities in Higher Education -- NFF/ETS -- Fellowship Information Working File -- General, 1977-1979 (Box 3)
  - Minorities in Higher Education -- NFF/ETS -- General -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports, Meeting Materials, etc. (1 of 2), 1976-1979 (Box 3)
  - Minorities in Higher Education -- NFF/ETS -- General -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports, Meeting Materials, etc. (2 of 2), 1978-1980 (Box 3)
  - Minorities in Higher Education -- NFF/ETS -- Howard Dressner Re: the Finnish Ruling and Discriminatory Awards, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - Minorities in Higher Education -- NFF/ETS -- PhD Statistics Re: Chronicle Article, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Fellowship Material, 1975-1979 (Box 4)
  - Recommendations for Grant/DAP Action (1 of 2), 1981 (Box 4)
  - Recommendations for Grant/DAP Action (2 of 2), 1981 (Box 4)
- Pending Grant Files, 1976-1983; III
  - American Association for the Advancement of the Humanities, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1983 (Box 4)
  - American Center in Paris, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, American Studies Program, 1982 (Box 4)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1983 (Box 4)
  - American Council on Education, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Arts International, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Asian Cultural Council, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Aspen Institute, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Association of American Universities, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Association Council for Policy Analysis and Research, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Brook, Peter, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Bryn Mawr College, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Carlos Chagas Foundation, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Carnegie Corporation -- Commission on College Retirement, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Carnegie Mellon University/Carnegie Corporation, Enhancing Student Learning with Information Technology, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Carnegie Mellon University, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Center for Applied Lingusitics -- PRI, 1978-1983 (Box 4)
  - Center for Creative Leadership, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - The College Board, 1981-1983 (Box 4)
  - College Entrance Examination Board (CEEB), Washington Policy Office, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Conference on Small Private Colleges, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - The Council of Graduate Schools in the United States, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Council on Library Resources, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Davis, John, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Education Commission of the States (ECS), 1983 (Box 4)
  - The Feminist Press, 1981-1983 (Box 4)
  - Five Colleges Incorporated, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Folger Library (Amherst College), 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - The Forum Institute, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Harvard University, Graduate School of Education, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Howard University Press Re: Publication of Book on Historically Black Colleges, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Hubert H. Humphrey Institutute of Public Affairs, University of Minnesota, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, New Jersey, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Institute of International Education (IIE), 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - International Council on the Future of the University, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Lapham, Lewis Re: Proposal for Historical Quarterly, 1977-1982 (Box 4)
  - Legal Defense Fund (LDF), 1983 (Box 4)
  - Library of America, 1980-1982 (Box 4)
  - Lynton, Ernest, 1983 (Box 4)
  - MALDEF (Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund) (1 of 2), 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - MALDEF (2 of 2), 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Malcolm-King -- Harlem College Extension, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Manley-CUPA (Frank B. Manley Company) Re: Salary Survey in Colleges and Universities Sponsored by the College and University Personnel Association, 1982 (Box 4)
  - University of Missouri - St. Louis, 1982 (Box 4)
  - MIT, undated (Box 4)
  - Moscoso, Teodoro (Munoz Marin Foundation), San Juan, Puerto Rico, 1983 (Box 4)
  - National Chicano Council on Higher Education (NCCHE), 1982 (Box 4)
  - National Public Radio (NPR), 1982 (Box 5)
  - New York University -- Model Faculty Resource Network, 1983 (Box 5)
  - North Carolina Central University, "Proposed Strategies to Improve Minority Student Retention in Higher Education", 1980-1982 (Box 5)
  - Opera Assessment, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Pace University, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Pennsylvania, University of, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - Southern Regional Education Board, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
  - Stanford University -- Center for Research on Women, 1976-1982 (Box 5)
  - Tougaloo College -- PRI, 1982 (Box 5)
  - WNET/Thirteen, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - Women's Equity Action League (WEAL), 1976-1982 (Box 5)
  - Women's Research and Education Institute, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
  - Women's Studies, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Woodrow Wilson Foundation, undated (Box 5)